<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Quick Start Guide - GeoNetwork opensource Version 2.1.0</title>

  <toc>
    <tocchap>
      <tocentry></tocentry>
    </tocchap>
  </toc>

  <chapter>
    <title>A Geographic Information Management System for all</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>GeoNetwork opensource (GNos) is a standard based and decentralized
      spatial information management system, designed to enable access to
      geo-referenced databases and cartographic products from a variety of
      data providers through descriptive metadata, enhancing the spatial
      information exchange and sharing between organizations and their
      audience, using the capacities and the power of the Internet. The system
      provides a broad community of users with easy and timely access to
      available spatial data and thematic maps from multidisciplinary sources,
      that may in the end support informed decision making. The main goal of
      the GNos software is to increase collaboration within and between
      organizations for reducing duplication and enhancing information
      consistency and quality and to improve the accessibility of a wide
      variety of geographic information along with the associated information,
      organized and documented in a standard and consistent way.</para>

      <highlights>
        <para>GeoNetwork Main Features</para>

        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Instant search on local and distributed geospatial
              catalogues</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Uploading and downloading of data, documents, PDF's and
              any other content</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>An interactive Web map viewer that combines Web Map
              Services from distributed servers around the world</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Online map layout generation and export in PDF
              format</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Online editing of metadata with a powerful template
              system</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Scheduled harvesting and syncronization of metadata
              between distributed catalogues</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Groups and users management</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Fine grained access control</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </highlights>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GeoNetwork opensource background and its evolution</title>

      <para>The prototype of the GeoNetwork catalog was developed by the Food
      and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) in 2001 to
      systematically archive and publish the geographic datasets produced
      within the Organization. The prototype was built on experiences within
      and outside the organization. It used metadata content available from
      legacy systems that was transformed into what was then only a draft
      metadata standard, the ISO 19115. Later on, another UN agency, the World
      Food Programme (WFP) joined the project and with its contribution the
      first version of the software was released in 2003 and operational
      catalogues were established in FAO and WFP. The system was based on the
      ISO19115:DIS metadata standard and embedded the Web Map Client InterMap
      that supported Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) compliant Web Map
      Services. Distributed searches were possible using the standard Z39.50
      catalog protocol. At that moment it was decided to develop the program
      as a Free and Open Source Software to allow the whole geospatial users
      community to benefit from the development results and to contribute to
      the further advancement of the software.</para>

      <para>Jointly with the UN Environmental Programme (UNEP), FAO developed
      a second version in 2004. The new release allowed users to work with
      multiple metadata standards (ISO 19115, FGDC and Dublin Core) in a
      transparent manner. It also allowed metadata to be shared between
      catalogues through a caching mechanism, improving reliability when
      searching in multiple catalogues.</para>

      <para>In 2006, the GeoNetwork team dedicated efforts to develop a DVD
      containing the GNos version 2.0.3 and the best free and open source
      software in the field of Geoinformatics. The DVD was produced and
      distributed in hard copy to over three thousand people and is now also
      available for download from the http://geonetwork-opensource.org Web
      site.</para>

      <para>The latest release of GNos version 2.1, issued in late 2007, is
      the result of another round of critical improvements, supported by FAO,
      the UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (UNOCHA), the
      Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CSI-CGIAR),
      UNEP and other donors. Support for the final metadata standard
      ISO19115:2003 has been enabled by using the ISO19139:2007 implementation
      specification schema published in May 2007. The release also serves as
      the open source reference implementation of the OGC Catalog Service for
      the Web (CSW 2.0.1) specification. Improvements to give users a more
      responsive and interactive experience have been substantial and include
      a new Web map viewer and a complete revision of search interface.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The use of Standards</title>

      <para>GNos has been developed following the principles of a Free and
      Open Source Software (FOSS) and based on International and Open
      Standards for services and protocols, like the ISO-TC211 and the Open
      Geospatial Consortium (OGC) specifications. The GeoNetwork architecture
      is largely compatible with the OGC Portal Reference Architecture, i.e.
      the OGC guide for implementing standardized geospatial portals. Indeed,
      the GNos’ own structure relies on the same three main modules identified
      by the OGC Portal Reference Architecture, that are focused on spatial
      data, metadata and interactive map visualization. GNos is also fully
      compliant with the OGC specifications for querying and retrieving
      information from Web catalogues (CSW 2.0.1). GNos supports the most
      common standards to specifically describe geographic data (ISO19139 and
      FGDC) and the international standard for general documents (Dublin
      Core). It uses standards (OGS WMS) also for visualizing maps through the
      Internet.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Harvesting geospatial data in a shared environment</title>

      <para>Within the geographic information environment, the increased
      collaboration between data providers and their efforts to reduce
      duplication have stimulated the development of tools and systems to
      significantly improve the information sharing and guarantee an easier
      and quicker access of data from a variety of sources without undermining
      the ownership of the information. The harvesting funcionality in GNos is
      a mechanism of data collection in perfect accordance with both rights to
      data access and data ownership protection. Through the harvesting
      functionality it is possible to collect public information from the
      different GeoNetwork nodes installed around the world and to copy and
      store periodically this information locally. In this way a user from a
      single entry point can get information also from distributed catalogues.
      The logo posted on top each harvested record informs the user about the
      data source.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GeoNetwork and the Open Source Community Development</title>

      <para>The community of users and developers of the GNos software has
      increased dramatically since the release of version 2.0 in December 2005
      and the subsequent pre-releases of version 2.1. At present, the user and
      developer mailing lists count nearly 200 subscriptions each.
      Subscription to these lists is open to anyone interested. The archive of
      the mailing lists provides an important resource for users and can be
      freely browsed online. Members provide feedback within the community and
      provide translations, new functionalities, bug reports, fixes and
      instructions to the project as a whole. Building a self sustaining
      community of users and developers is one of the biggest challenges for
      the project. This community-building process relies on active
      participation and interaction of its members. It also relies on building
      trust and operating in a transparent manner, thereby agreeing on the
      overall objectives, prioritization and long term direction of the
      project. A number of actions have been taken by the project team to
      facilitate this process.</para>

      <para>The foundation for the establishment of a GeoNetwork Advisory
      Board was laid at the 2006 workshop in Rome and membership criteria were
      defined.</para>

      <para>A work plan is presented and discussed at the yearly GNos
      workshop; subsequently, the plan is maintained and updated throughout
      the year where needed. The project management team reports back to the
      advisory board about the reached developments and objectives during the
      annual workshops.</para>

      <para>Two public Websites have been established. One focuses on the
      users of the software (http://geonetwork-opensource.org), while the
      other one is dedicated to the developers
      (http://trac-osgeo.org/geonetwork). Both can be updated and maintained
      online by trusted members of the community. They provide documentation,
      bug reporting and tracking, Wiki pages et cetera. A small part of the
      community connects through Internet Relay Chat (IRC) on a public
      geonetwork channel. But most interaction takes place on the user and the
      developer mailing lists.</para>

      <para>During the 2006 workshop, the project advisory board decided to
      propose the GeoNetwork opensource project as an incubator project to the
      newly founded Open Source Geospatial Foundation (OSGEO). This incubation
      process is currently ongoing but close to conclusions. The project
      Websites has been moved to servers accessible under the umbrella of the
      OSGEO foundation. Web pages have been updated to reflect the OSGEO
      principles and a source code review performed.</para>

      <para>Source code is maintained in a publicly accessible code
      repository, hosted at an independent service provider, SourceForge.net
      that hosts thousands of FOSS projects. Developers and users have full
      access to all sections of the source code, while trusted developers can
      make changes in the repository itself. A special mailing list has been
      established to monitor changes in the code repository. This so-called
      "commit mailing list" delivers change reports by email to its
      subscribers.</para>

      <para>Standardizing documentation development is the next challenge
      taken up by the project to ensure versioning and support of multiple
      output formats (e.g. HTML and PDF).</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Metadata Theoretical concepts</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>What is Metadata?</title>

      <para>Metadata, commonly defined as “data about data”, is a structured
      set of information which describes data (including both digital and
      non-digital datasets) stored in administrative systems. Metadata may
      provide a short summary about the content, purpose, quality, location of
      the data as well as information related to its creation.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>What are Metadata Standards?</title>

      <para>Metadata standards provide data producers with the format and
      content for properly describing their data, allowing users to evaluate
      the usefulness of the data in addressing their specific needs.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Why do we need Standardized Metadata?</title>

      <para>Standardized metadata support users in effectively and efficiently
      accessing data by using a common set of terminology and metadata
      elements that allow for a quick means of data discovery and retrieval
      from metadata clearinghouses. The metadata based on standards ensure
      information consistency and quality and avoid that important parts of
      data knowledge are lost.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Geographic Information Metadata Standard</title>

      <para>Geographic data, which can be defined as any data with a
      geographic component, is often produced by one individual or
      organization, and may address the needs of various users, including
      information system analysts, programme planners, developers of
      geographic information or policy makers. Proper standard documentation
      on geographic data enable different users to better evaluate the
      appropriateness of data to be used for data production, storage,
      update.</para>

      <para>The metadata standards supported by GeoNetwork opensource are the
      <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">ISO
      19115</emphasis>:2003</emphasis> - approved by the international
      community in April 2003 as a tool to define metadata in the field of
      geographic information - and the <emphasis role="bold">FGDC</emphasis> -
      the metadata standard adopted in the United States by the Federal
      Geographic Data Committee. In addition, GNos supports also the
      international standard <emphasis role="bold">Dublin Core</emphasis> for
      the description of general documents.</para>

      <para>This ISO Standard precisely defines how geographic information and
      related services should be described, providing mandatory and
      conditional metadata sections, metadata entities and metadata elements.
      This standard applies to data series, independent datasets, individual
      geographic features and feature properties. Despite ISO 19115:2003 was
      designed for digital data, its principles can be extended to many other
      forms of geographic data such as maps, charts, and textual documents as
      well as non-geographic data (ISO/FDIS 19115, 2003).</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Get connected to the new release!</title>

    <section>
      <title>New version - New funtionalities</title>

      <para>GeoNetwork opensource version 2.1.0 comes with substantial
      upgrades of different components for a more intuitive and responsive
      user-system interaction. Web2 technologies have been adopted, in
      particular AJAX techniques, to allow for more interactive and faster
      services in the web interface and for the integration of the existing
      web map viewer in the home page. Similar functionalities have been
      implemented in the administrative part of the system, to provide an
      easier access to the configuration pages related to site settings,
      catalogue harvesting, scheduling and maintenance.</para>

      <para>The search interface has been completely overhauled to provide
      highly interactive searching capabilities. Furthermore, the new version
      of GNos embeds GeoServer as map server. Users can now not only overlay
      OGC web map services available on the web, but also create their own map
      services for other users to browse without having to download additional
      plugins. Maps created with web map services can be now saved as PDF and
      sent to others.</para>

      <para>The metadata catalogue handles the latest ISO19115:2003 geographic
      metadata format based on the ISO191139 schemas, as well as the older
      ISO19115 final draft format, FGDC and Dublin Core. The metadata editor
      is able to handle the majority of these complex standards, providing
      default, advanced and XML editing online tools.</para>

      <para>The new version has a number of different harvesting interfaces
      allowing users to connect their own server to many other catalogues
      around the world. This is the result of the implementation of the open
      source reference for the web catalog services according to OGC
      specifications. Harvesting in the new version is now fully compatible
      with GeoNetwork 2.0 and 2.1 nodes.</para>

      <para>We have added avanced online and offline administration
      funcionalities to configure, backup and migrate the application. We have
      also added a convenient import and export format "MEF" or Metadata
      Exchange Format, that allows the users to move metadata, previews and
      even data in a convenient single file. GNos can be easily expanded with
      plugins to export/import metadata to/from other software supporting
      MEF.</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Figure 3.1. Home page of the GeoNetwork
        opensource version 2.1.0</emphasis></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/Home_page_s.png" scale="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Where do I get the GeoNetwork opensource installer?</title>

      <para>You can find the Geonetwork opensource software on the Internet at
      the GeoNetwork opensource Community website
      http://geonetwork-opensource.org. The new version 2.1.0 is also
      distributed through the Sourceforge Website at
      http://sourceforge.net/projects/geonetwork.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>System requirements</title>

      <para>The GNos can run either on <emphasis role="bold">MS
      Windows</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Linux</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="bold">Mac OS X</emphasis>.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para>Some general system requirements for the software to run without
      problems are listed below:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Processor</emphasis>: 1 GHz or higher</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Memory (RAM)</emphasis>: 512 MB or
      higher</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Disk Space</emphasis>: 30 MB minimum.
      However, it is suggested to have a minimum of 250 MB of free disk space.
      Additional space is required depending on the amount of spatial data
      that you expect to upload into the internal geodatabse.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Other Software requirements</emphasis>: A
      Java Runtime Environment (JRE 1.5.0). For server installations, Apache
      Tomcat and a dedicated JDBC compliant DBMS (MySQL, Oracle) are also
      required.<emphasis role="bold"></emphasis></para>

      <para></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Supporting Software</emphasis></para>

      <para>-Java Runtime Environment (JRE 1.4.0 +) (Windows &amp;
      Linux)</para>

      <para>-MySQL DBMS v5.5 (All)*</para>

      <para>-Apache Tomcat v5.5 (All)*</para>

      <para>-Apache HTTP v2.0 (Windows)</para>

      <para>-Druid v3.8 (All)*</para>

      <para>-Firefox v1.5 (All)*</para>

      <para>-Internet Explorer (Windows)</para>

      <para></para>

      <para>* All = Windows, Linux and Mac OS X</para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How do I install GeoNetwork opensource?</title>

      <para>Before running the GeoNetwork installer, make sure that all system
      requirements are satisfied, and in particular that the Java Runtime
      Environment version 1.5.0 is set up on your machine.</para>

      <para>If you use Windows, the following steps will guide you to complete
      the installation (other FOSS will follow):</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Double click on <emphasis
          role="bold">geonetwork-install-2.1.0.exe</emphasis> to start the
          GeoNetwok opensource desktop installer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Follow the instructions on screen (figure 3.4)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>After completion of the installation process, a 'GeoNetwork
          desktop' menu will be added to your Windows Start menu under
          'Programs'</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click Start &gt; Programs &gt; GeoNetwork desktop &gt; Start
          server to start the Geonetwork opensource Web server. The first time
          you do this, the system will require about 1 minute to complete
          startup.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click Start &gt; Programs &gt; Geonetwork desktop &gt; Open
          GeoNetwork opensource to start using GeoNetwork opensource, or
          connect your Web browser to http://localhost8080/geonetwork/</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 3.4</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/installer.png" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><guilabel></guilabel></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>There are no requirements for general visitors to search and access
    information in a GeoNetwork opensource based catalog. To get access to
    advanced features and restricted information, you need an account to log
    in (e.g. a username and password) that should be provided by the GNos
    administrator. Depending on your privileges, you will be able to access,
    submit and edit metadata records. Each user is assigned to a particular
    work group and is able to access data within that work group. To log in,
    simply go to the homepage and enter your username and password in the
    dedicated fields on the top right corner, then click the login button.
    (See figure 4)</para>

    <para></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Figure 4</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/login.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Searching for Maps and Data</title>

    <para>There are many different ways to search the catalogue for maps and
    other geographic data. This guide will introduce you to the most popular
    search methods: default, advanced and by category. Whichever search you
    choose, remember that you will see results based on your privileges and
    assigned work group.</para>

    <para>Note that the term <emphasis role="bold">data</emphasis> in this
    application refers to datasets, maps, tables, documents, etc. that are
    linked to the metadata of a specific record.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Default Search</title>

      <para>The default search allows you to search text within the entire
      record, such as keywords of the metadata and/or geographic
      location.</para>

      <para>For the free text search:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Enter</emphasis></emphasis> a
          search term or letter(s) in the <emphasis
          role="bold">What?</emphasis> field. You can use one or more thematic
          keyword(s) or strings in quotes. Keywords and operators (and, or,
          not) are not case sensitive. (See figure 5.1 a).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.1 a</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/what.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>For the geographic search, two options are available for selecting
      a particular region to limit the search:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can select a <emphasis
          role="bold">region</emphasis><emphasis
          role="bold"><emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis> from
          </emphasis><emphasis>a</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis><emphasis
          role="bold"> predefined list</emphasis></emphasis>. (Figure 5.1
          b);</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.1 b</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/where1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can select your own <emphasis role="bold">area of
          interest</emphasis> in a more interactive way. A <emphasis
          role="bold"><emphasis>small global map is shown on the screen from
          which you can </emphasis></emphasis>drag and drop the frame of your
          location area. Just click on the button on the upper right of the
          map screen.<emphasis role="bold"><emphasis> (Figure 5.1
          c)</emphasis></emphasis>;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.1 c</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/where2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <para>Both types of search, free text search and geographic search can
      be combined to restrict the query further.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis> button.
            (Figure 5.1 e).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Fogure 5.1 e</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/search_button.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Searching by Categories</title>

      <para>An additional way to search data within the GeoNetwork database,
      from the home page, is searching by <emphasis
      role="bold">Category</emphasis>. A list of categories is provided to the
      user to identify data at a more generic level: <emphasis
      role="bold">Applications</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">Audio/Video</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Case study and
      best practices</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Conference
      proceedings</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Datasets</emphasis>,
      <emphasis role="bold">Directories</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">Interactive resources</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Maps
      and graphics</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Other information
      resources</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Photo</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>To search only for maps, click on <emphasis role="bold">Maps and
      Graphics</emphasis> (Figure 5.2). A list of maps will be displayed from
      which you may view details of every single map; just clicking on the
      <emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> button of the map you wish to
      review.</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.2</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/Categories.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Advanced Search</title>

      <para>The advanced search option (Figure 5.3 a) works similarly to the
      default search. However, you can be more specific in your search
      criteria as it offers different elements to look for data, each of them
      answering one of the following questions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">WHAT?</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">WHERE?</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">WHEN?</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.3 a</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/advanced_search1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <para>To perform an <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>advanced
      search</emphasis></emphasis>, from the home page <emphasis
      role="bold">click</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Advanced
      </emphasis>just below the search bottom (see figure 5.3 from the default
      search section).</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.3</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/advanced_search_button.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">WHAT?</emphasis> section the elements
      are all related to the data content. Through them, in addition to
      searching only free keywords in the entire metadata content, you can
      also search directly in the title or abstract fields and add more
      keywords to customize your search further. You can also specify the
      level of accuracy you wish to reach in performing your search. (Figure
      5.3 b).</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To search by <emphasis role="bold">Title</emphasis>, <emphasis
          role="bold">Abstract</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Free
          Text</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">Keyword</emphasis>(s) type
          any text into the respective field. You can enter information in one
          or multiple field(s). If you do not want to search by a given field,
          simply leave it blank;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can choose the <emphasis role="bold">accuracy of your
          search</emphasis>, in terms of spelling words, from <emphasis
          role="bold">Precise</emphasis> = 1 to <emphasis
          role="bold">Imprecise</emphasis> = 0.2, through 3 more consecutive
          steps which are equal to 0.8, 0.6, 0.4.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.3 b</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/advanced_search_what.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">WHERE?</emphasis> parameters, which are
      related to the spatial extent, allow you, as in the default search,
      either to select your own area of interest or to select a predefined
      region from the drop-down list. In this section you can also type the
      geographic coordinates of a specific location that is not available from
      the above list. (Figure 5.3 c)</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To select <emphasis role="bold">your own area of
          interest</emphasis>, drag and drop the frame of your area on the
          global map using the appropriate tool on the bottom left of the map
          screen;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To use <emphasis role="bold">free coordinates</emphasis>, type
          the lat-long geographic references in the appropriate fields around
          the map screen, without any limitation of decimal figures;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To use the coordinates of a <emphasis role="bold">predefined
          region</emphasis>, select the region from the drop-down list.</para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.3 c</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/advanced_search_where.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <para>Whatever type of geographic search you decide to perform, in the
      <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search type</emphasis> field, you can
      choose from different options: <emphasis role="bold">is</emphasis>,
      <emphasis role="bold">overlaps</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="bold">encloses</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">is fully outside
      of</emphasis> (Figure 5.3 c). If you use this field, be cautious as this
      limits your output data as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search
          type</emphasis> <citetitle>is</citetitle> “Country”, only maps for
          the selected country will be displayed. In other words, a city map
          within that country will not show in the output results.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search
          type</emphasis> <citetitle>overlaps</citetitle> “Country”, all maps
          with the bounding box overlapping that country will be displayed in
          the results, i.e. the neighbouring countries, the continent of which
          that country is part of and the global maps.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search
          type</emphasis> <citetitle>encloses</citetitle> “Country” you will
          get, in the output results, maps of that country first and then all
          maps within its bounding box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Similarly, if you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search
          type</emphasis> <citetitle>is fully outside of</citetitle> a
          selected region, only maps that follow that exact criteria will show
          in the output results.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">WHEN?</emphasis> section gives you the
      possibility to restrict your search in terms of temporal extent,
      indicating a specific range of time referred to the data creation or
      publication date (figure 5.3 d).</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To specify a range of time, click on the date selector button
          next to <emphasis role="bold">From – To</emphasis> fields. Make use
          of the symbols<emphasis role="bold"> &gt;</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="bold">&gt;&gt;</emphasis> on top of the calendar to select the
          month and the year first and then click on the exact day; a complete
          date will be filled in using the following standard order:
          YY-MM-DD.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To clean the time fields, simply click on the white cross on
          their right; the box <emphasis role="bold">Any</emphasis> will be
          automatically selected and the search will be performed without any
          restriction on the time period.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.3 d</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/advanced_search_when.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Finally, the advanced search allows you to apply further
      restrictions on the basis of additional parameters as data source, data
      categories and data format (see figure 5.3 e).</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To limit your queries to only one <emphasis
          role="bold">Catalog</emphasis> out of those made available by the
          installation through the harvesting process, highlight the catalog
          of preference or just keep <emphasis role="bold">Any</emphasis>
          selected to search all sites. (See more info about <emphasis
          role="bold">data harvesting</emphasis> in Section 4 Chapter 1 of
          these guidelines).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To search for data organized by <emphasis
          role="bold">Category</emphasis>, such as Applications, Datasets,
          etc., simply highlight the category you wish to search in from the
          related drop-down list, otherwise we suggest to leave this field in
          <emphasis role="bold">Any</emphasis> Category.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can search for <emphasis role="bold">Digital</emphasis> or
          <emphasis role="bold">Hard Copy</emphasis> maps. To search in one or
          the other, simply check the box next to the one you wish to search.
          If no box is checked, all content will be searched.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>At last, you can customize the number of output results per page
      in the <emphasis role="bold">Hits Per Page</emphasis> field. Simply
      highlight the number of records to be displayed or leave the field set
      on the default number (10).</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis>
          button.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 5.3 e</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/advanced_search_morerest.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Analyzing Search Results</title>

      <para>The output of a search provides you a list of the metadata records
      that should fit your request. For each record, the result page shows the
      title, an abstract and the keywords. According to the privileges that
      have been set for each metadata, a maximum of four sections can be
      consulted, as shown below. (Figure 5.4)</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Figure 5.4</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/search_output2.png" scale="" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para></para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis>: The metadata
          section describes the dataset (e.g.: citation, data owner,
          temporal/spatial/methodological information) and could contain links
          to other web sites that could provide further information about the
          dataset.</para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Download</emphasis>: Depending on the
          privileges that have been set for each record, when this button is
          present, the dataset is available and downloadable. The downloadable
          package is in a compressed format and contains the data and any
          document or pictures can be included with the primary resources.
          Note: the actual size of the compressed package can't exceed 50 Mb.
          The process for retrieving data is simple and quick by just clicking
          the download button (fig.5.4.2 a) or by using the proper link in the
          specific metadata section for distribution info (fig.4.4.2
          b).</para>

          <para></para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Figure 5.4.2 a</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/search_output1.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Figure 5.4.2 b</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/download.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Interactive Map</emphasis>: The map
          service is also optional. When this button is shown, an interactive
          map for this layer is available and, by default, it will be
          displayed on the map screen of the simple search. To better
          visualize the map through the map viewer, <emphasis
          role="bold">click</emphasis> on <emphasis role="bold">Open Map
          Viewer</emphasis> on the bottom left of the map screen (figure
          5.4.3).</para>

          <para></para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Figure 5.4.3</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/interactive_map.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Graphic Overviews</emphasis>: There are
          small and large overviews of the map used to properly evaluate
          usefulness of the data, especially if the interactive map is not
          available. Simply click on the small image to enlarge it. (Figure
          5.4.4)</para>

          <para></para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Figure 5.4.4</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/thumbnail.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Viewing and Analyzing the Data</title>

    <para>Once you have completed your search, you view details of a
    particular record by clicking on the <emphasis
    role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> button.</para>

    <para>The metadata profiles used by GNos to present and describe
    geographic data and general documents stored in the catalogue are based on
    the<emphasis role="bold"> International Standard</emphasis> <emphasis
    role="bold">ISO 19115</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">:2003</emphasis>,
    encoded according to the <emphasis role="bold">implementation
    schema</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">19139:2007</emphasis>, the
    <emphasis role="bold">FGDC</emphasis> and the international standard
    <emphasis role="bold">Dublin Core</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>In this guide the <emphasis role="bold">ISO 19139</emphasis>
    metadata implementation will be described in details since it is also
    suggested as profile for the creation of new metadata records.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Meta Data Description</title>

      <para>The metadata ISO 19139 profile used by GeoNetwork opensource to
      describe the geographic data and services is based on the ISO standard
      19115:2003 and provides information related to the identification, the
      maintenance and constraints, the spatial and temporal extent, the
      spatial representation and reference, the quality and distribution of a
      geographic dataset.</para>

      <para>The metadata profile is organized in sections and the most
      important, illustrated in the figure 6.1, are the: <emphasis
      role="bold">Identification Section, Distribution Section, Reference
      System Section, Data Quality Section and Metadata Section</emphasis>.
      These sections are described here in details.</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 6.1</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/mainSections.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Identification Section</title>

        <para>This section includes information on the citation of the
        resource (<emphasis role="bold">title, date of creation or
        publication, edition, presentation form</emphasis>), the <emphasis
        role="bold">abstract</emphasis>, the <emphasis
        role="bold">purpose</emphasis> and the present<emphasis role="bold">
        status</emphasis> of the resource that can be defined among the
        options: completed, historical archive, obsolete, ongoing, planned,
        required or under development. (Figure 6.1.1 a).</para>

        <para></para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Figure 6.1.1 a</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/Ident_Info_1.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>This section also contains information about the person or
        organization responsible for the data and who is considered to be a
        <emphasis role="bold">point of contact</emphasis> for the resource
        i.e. the dataset owner, originator, distributor, publisher, etc. and
        it provides information on <emphasis role="bold">data
        maintenance</emphasis> i.e. annually, monthly, daily, not planned, as
        needed, etc. (Figure 6.1.1 b)</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.1 b</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/PoC_Maint.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para>Elements for <emphasis role="bold">keywords</emphasis> and for
        describing restrictions on <emphasis role="bold">data</emphasis>
        <emphasis role="bold">access</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">use</emphasis> are also included in this section in
        addition to <emphasis role="bold">spatial <emphasis
        role="bold">representation</emphasis> </emphasis>info like data type
        (vector, raster, text table, etc.) (figure 6.1.1 c).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.1 c</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/Key_Const_Spatype.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para>The identification section provides information about the
        <emphasis role="bold">scale</emphasis>, the <emphasis
        role="bold">language</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">character
        set</emphasis> used within the resource and the list of <emphasis
        role="bold">ISO categories</emphasis> through which your map could be
        classified (figure 6.1.1 d).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.1 d</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/scale.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para>Finally, the temporal and spatial extent are also defined in
        this section. The temporal extent is defined through the starting and
        ending date of data validation (Figure 6.1.1 e);</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis role="bold">Figure 6.1.1 e</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/temp_extent.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para>The spatial extent of the interested area is defined through
        geographic coordinates or through the selection of a country or region
        from a predefined list (Figure 6.1.1 f). Free text <emphasis
        role="bold">supplemental information</emphasis> can be added to
        complete the data identification section.</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title><emphasis role="bold">Figure 6.1.1 f</emphasis></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/geobox.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Distribution Section</title>

        <para>This section provides metadata elements for <emphasis
        role="bold">accessing</emphasis> other useful <emphasis
        role="bold">on-line resources</emphasis> available <emphasis
        role="bold">through the web</emphasis>. The distribution elements
        allow for on-line access using an URL address or similar addressing
        scheme and provide the protocol for the proper connection <emphasis
        role="bold">for accessing geographic data</emphasis> or any other
        types of digital documents <emphasis role="bold">using the
        download</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">function</emphasis>.
        Furthermore, it is possible <emphasis role="bold">to link</emphasis> a
        metadata with a <emphasis role="bold">predefined map
        service</emphasis> through the <emphasis role="bold">on line
        resource</emphasis> and see the map interactively (Figure
        6.1.2).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.2</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/distrInfo.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Reference System Section</title>

        <para>The Spatial Reference System section <emphasis
        role="bold">defines</emphasis> <emphasis
        role="bold">metadata</emphasis> required <emphasis role="bold">to
        describe</emphasis> the <emphasis role="bold">spatial reference
        system</emphasis> of a dataset. It contains one element to identify
        the name of the reference system used (Figure 6.1.3). Using elements
        <emphasis role="bold">from the advanced form</emphasis>, this section
        may be modified to provide more <emphasis
        role="bold">details</emphasis> on <emphasis role="bold">data
        projection</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">ellipsoid</emphasis> and
        <emphasis role="bold">datum</emphasis>. Note that if this information
        is provided, a reference system identifier is not mandatory.</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.3</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/RefSystem.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Data Quality Section</title>

        <para>The Data Quality section provides a <emphasis
        role="bold">general assessment</emphasis> of the <emphasis
        role="bold">quality of the data</emphasis>. It describes the<emphasis
        role="bold"> different hierarchical levels of data quality</emphasis>,
        namely a <emphasis role="bold">dataset series</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">dataset</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">features</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">attributes</emphasis>, etc. This section also contains
        information about <emphasis role="bold">sources of the input
        data</emphasis>, and a<emphasis role="bold"> general explanation of
        the production processes</emphasis> (lineage) used for creating the
        data (Figure 6.1.4).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.4</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/dataQuality.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Metadata Information Section</title>

        <para>This section contains information about the metadata itself: the
        <emphasis role="bold">Global Unique Identifier</emphasis> (GUID)
        assigned to the record (this is the ‘File identifier’), <emphasis
        role="bold">language</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">character</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">set</emphasis>
        used, <emphasis role="bold">date</emphasis> of <emphasis
        role="bold">la</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">st edit</emphasis>
        (‘Date stamp’) and the <emphasis role="bold">metadata
        standard</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">version name</emphasis>
        of the record. It also contains information on the <emphasis
        role="bold">metadata author</emphasis> responsible for the metadata
        record; this person can also be a point of contact for the resource
        described. Information on the Metadata author is mandatory (figure
        6.1.5).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 6.1.5</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/metadata.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Adding new Data and Information</title>

    <para>This section guides you through the process of adding new records
    (new data with information) into the GeoNetwork catalogue using either the
    online metadata editor or the advanced metadata insert tool, based on XML
    documents. In both cases you will use the template system, add thumbnails,
    upload data, link to services and set access privileges to the metadata
    and data.</para>

    <para>To add or edit data and metadata, you must be <emphasis
    role="bold">registered</emphasis> as an <emphasis
    role="bold">Editor</emphasis> into the work group you want to add records
    to. Contact your administrator if you are not a registered editor for your
    work group.</para>

    <para>For the metadata creation using the online editor, GNos provides a
    set of simplified metadata templates based on the cited standards: ISO,
    FGDC and DC. The templates for vector and raster based on the ISO 19139
    are the preferred ones since they are devised in a way that hides the
    complexity of the ISO19115 standard in the default view. At the same time
    those templates are extensible with new elements to fit specialized needs
    through the advanced view.</para>

    <para>To produce a good metadata record, always try to gather as much
    details as possible on the resource that you want to describe taking into
    account the metadata elements that have been presented in the previous
    chapter. The next step is to fill out properly the fields provided by the
    metadata templates, while at the same time avoiding duplication of
    information throughout the form.</para>

    <para>The most important fields that may not be waived while compiling a
    standard based metadata record are the following: <emphasis
    role="bold">Title, Date of Creation o Publication, Abstract, Language used
    for documenting data, Topic Category, Scale, Maintenance and Update
    Frequency, Metadata Author, Language Used for Documenting
    Metadata</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>In addition to the main mandatory fields, we recommend you to fill
    out these optional but critical fields (if information is available):
    <emphasis role="bold">Purpose - Keywords - Presentation Form - Status -
    Spatial Representation Type - Geographic Location - Reference System Info
    - Temporal Extent - Data Quality Info - Access and Use Constraints - Point
    of Contact - Distribution Info: Online Resources.</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis><emphasis>You should also prepare an image of your data
    that is required to be displayed in search results as
    thumbnail.</emphasis></emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis><emphasis>Next section will guide you through the process
    of metadata creation using the online editor.</emphasis></emphasis></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Creating a New Record using the Metadata Editor on line</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the home page, click on the <emphasis
          role="bold">Administration Tab</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">New Metadata</emphasis> from the
          List of the admin page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the metadata standard <emphasis
          role="bold">Template</emphasis>, if possible, using the preferred
          ones (figure 6.1 c). GeoNetwork opensource comes by default with
          support for three metadata standards, ISO19139, FGDC and Dublin
          core. For the ISO standard, two templates have been developed; one
          for vector and one for raster data. Both contain a relevant set of
          elements to describe the respective types of data. More templates
          can be developed online.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Group</emphasis> the metadata
          will belong to. These are the groups authorized to add metadata to
          by your administrator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Create</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>The steps in more details</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter your username and password and click on the login
            button (figure 7.1.1 a). The system will identify you and assign
            the correct privileges to work with.</para>

            <para></para>

            <figure>
              <title>Figure 7.1.1 a</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/login.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open the Administration page by clicking the Administration
            button in the banner and then click on the New metadata link
            (figure 7.1.1 b).</para>

            <para></para>

            <figure>
              <title>Figure 7.1.1 b</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/Admin.png" scale="" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the metadata creation page, select the metadata
            standard to use from the dropdown list (see figure 7.1.1 c)</para>

            <para></para>

            <para><figure>
                <title>Figure 7.1.1 c</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/metadataCreation.png" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure></para>

            <para></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>After selecting the correct template, you should identify
            which group of users the metadata will belong to (figure 7.1.1 d)
            and finally click on <emphasis
            role="bold">Create</emphasis>.</para>

            <para></para>

            <figure>
              <title>Figure 7.1.1 d</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../images/selectGroup.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para></para>

            <para>A new metadata form based on the selected template will be
            displayed for you to fill out.</para>

            <para></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Switching Editing Views from Default to Advanced to XML
        View</title>

        <para>Once you create a new record, you can choose between <emphasis
        role="bold">Default</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">XML
        View</emphasis>. To switch view, simply click on the view you want to
        switch to on the left column of the page. The view in <emphasis
        role="bold">bold</emphasis> is the view you are currently using (see
        figure 7.1.2 a).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.1.2 a</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/switchViews.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para>In the previous chapter you have analyzed the metadata structure
        as it is presented in the <emphasis role="bold">Default
        View</emphasis>. A selection of the main fields from different
        categories of information is shown in one single view. The minimum set
        of metadata required to serve the full range of metadata applications
        (data discovery, determination of data fitness for use, data access,
        data transfer and use of digital data) is defined here, along with
        optional metadata elements to allow for a more extensive standard
        description of geographic data, if required. However, if should be
        there a need to add more metadata elements, you can switch to the
        advanced view at any time while editing.</para>

        <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">Advanced View</emphasis>, the ISO
        profile offers the possibility to visualize and edit the entire
        metadata structure organized in sections accessible through tabs from
        the left column. You can use this view to write more advanced metadata
        descriptions or templates to fit specialized needs. (Figure 7.1.2
        b)</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.1.2 b</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/advancedView.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">XML View</emphasis> shows the entire
        content of the metadata in the original hierarchical structure;
        different colors allow to distinguish between an element's name and
        its value. The XML structure is composed of tags and to every tag must
        correspond a closing tag; the content is entirely contained withing
        the two, i.e.</para>

        <para>&lt;gmd:language&gt;</para>

        <para>&lt;gco:CharacterString&gt;eng&lt;/gco:CharacterString&gt;</para>

        <para>&lt;/gmd:language&gt;</para>

        <para>(see figure 7.1.2 c).</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Figure 7.1.2 c</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/xmlView1.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para>Nevertheless, the use of the XML view requires some knowledge of
        the XML language.</para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Both the <emphasis role="bold">Default</emphasis> and the
        <emphasis role="bold">Advanced Views</emphasis> are composed of
        <emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">conditional</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">optional</emphasis> metadata <emphasis
        role="bold">fields</emphasis>. The meaning of mandatory and optional
        is fairly intuitive; the mandatory fields are required and may not be
        waived, like <firstterm>Title</firstterm> and
        <firstterm>Abstract</firstterm> for instance, whereas the optional
        fields can be provided but are not fundamental, depending on the
        metadata author. The conditional fields may be considered mandatory
        under certain circumstances: essentially a conditional requirement
        indicates that the presence of a specified data element is dependent
        on the value or presence of other data elements in the same section.
        For instance, the <firstterm>Individual name</firstterm> metadata
        element of the <firstterm>Point of Contact</firstterm>, which is a
        conditional element of the Identification section, becomes mandatory
        if another element of the same section, <firstterm>Organization
        name</firstterm> or <firstterm>Position name</firstterm> is not
        already defined (figure 6.1.1 b).</para>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">mandatory fields</emphasis> as well as
        those <emphasis role="bold">highly recommended</emphasis> are flagged
        with <emphasis role="bold">red asterisk</emphasis> <emphasis
        role="bold">[<emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis>]</emphasis>. The
        standard definition for each field can be read by passing the mouse on
        the element name.</para>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Default View</emphasis> is the
        preferred view as it provides a selection of the available metadata
        elements, facilitating both the user and the editor in reading and
        editing a metadata record, and at the same time it ensures that a
        geospatial data can be properly described, through :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the minimum set of metadata required to serve the full range
            of metadata applications (data discovery, determination of data
            fitness for use, data access, data transfer, and use of digital
            data);</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>optional metadata elements - to allow for a more extensive
            standard description of geographic data, if required;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>a method for extending metadata to fit specialized
            needs.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Using basic commands of the editor</title>

        <para>Fields are either <emphasis role="bold">free text
        fields</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">drop down lists</emphasis>.
        Free text means you can type any text into that field. Drop down lists
        allow you to select only one option from the list. You can add
        multiple fields of the same kind by clicking on the <emphasis
        role="bold">[+]</emphasis> symbol next to the element. Every new field
        that you will add in the advanced view will then be visible in the
        default view. You can also delete existing fields by clicking on the
        <emphasis role="bold">[x]</emphasis> symbol next to the element.
        Clearly, mandatory fields cannot be deleted. One example of the need
        to add multiple fields can arise if the content of your dataset has
        some text written in two different languages (see figure
        7.1.3).</para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.1.3</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/multipleElement.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Entering Metadata for your Map</title>

      <para>As we mentioned in the introduction to this guide, GNos provides
      tools to describe any type of geographic data (verctor layers, raster,
      tables, map services, etc.) as well as general document like reports,
      projects, papers, etc. For the purpose of this Quick Start Guide, an
      example of required and useful metadata elements to properly describe a
      thematic map will be provided hereafter. You should gather as much
      information as possible to identify and understand the map’s resource
      and characteristics you want to describe. Use the default view to start.
      If necessary, you can always switch to advanced view or come back later
      and edit the record with the additonal information collected.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Entering Metadata For Your Map</title>

        <para>Please follow these steps to enter your map's metadata. Note
        that we will only go through the fields that have been identified as
        compulsory (i.e. those fields marked with the asterix <emphasis
        role="bold">[*],</emphasis> mandatory or highly recommended).</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Title </emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis>: Under the
        <emphasis role="bold">Identification Info</emphasis> field, give your
        map a <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>. There will be a default
        name of your data. Use free text to describe your map here.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Date <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
        role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>: Indicate the exact
        <emphasis role="bold">date</emphasis> of <emphasis
        role="bold">creation</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">publication</emphasis> or <emphasis
        role="bold">revision</emphasis> on your map.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Presentation Form</emphasis>: Specify the
        type of presentation, i.e. <emphasis role="bold">digital</emphasis>,
        <emphasis role="bold">hard copy</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">table</emphasis>, etc.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Abstract <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
        role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>: Enter some description
        of the map.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>: Enter a short summary
        of the purposes for your map to be developed.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Specify the status of
        your map within the following options: completed, historical archive,
        obsolete, ongoing, planned, required, under development.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Point of Contact</emphasis>: Enter all
        mandatory information and others you have at hand for the contact of
        the person(s) associated with this resources of the map. Note that
        some fields are only conditionally mandatory, such as Organization
        Name if Individual Name and Position are not entered.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Maintenance and update
        frequency</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
        role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis>: Specify the frequency with which
        you expect to make changes and additions to your map after the initial
        version is completed. If any changes are scheduled you can leave
        <firstterm>As Needed</firstterm> selected from the drop-down
        list.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Descriptive Keywords</emphasis>: Enter
        keywords that describe your map. Also specify the type of keyword you
        are entering, i.e. place, theme, etc. Remember that you can add
        another keyword field if you need to add different types of
        keywords.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Access Constraints</emphasis>: Enter an
        access constraint here, such as a copyright, trademark, etc. to assure
        the protection of privacy and intellectual property.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">User Constraints</emphasis>: Enter a user
        constraint here to assure the protection of privacy and intellectual
        property.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Other Constraints</emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold"><emphasis role="bold"> *</emphasis></emphasis>: Enter
        other constraint here to assure the protection of privacy and
        intellectual property. Note that this field is conditionally mandatory
        if Access and Use constraints are not entered.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Spatial representation type</emphasis>:
        Select, from the drop-down list the method used to spatially represent
        your data. The options are: vector, grid, text table, stereo model,
        video.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Scale Denominator <emphasis
        role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>:
        Enter the denominator for an equivalent scale of a hard copy of the
        map.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Language<emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
        role="bold"> *</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>: Select the language
        used within your map</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Topic category </emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis>: Specify the
        main ISO category/ies through which your map could be classified (see
        Annex for the complete list of ISO topic categories).</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Temporal Extent</emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis></emphasis>: Enter the
        starting and ending date of the validity period.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Geographic Bounding
        Box</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">
        *</emphasis></emphasis>: Enter the longitude and latitude for the map
        or select a region from the predefined drop-down list. Make sure you
        use degrees for the unit of the geographic coordinates as they are the
        basis for the geographic searches.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Supplemental Information</emphasis>: Enter
        any other descriptive information about your map that can help the
        user to better understand its content.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Distribution Info</emphasis>: Enter
        information about the distributor and about options for obtaining your
        map.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Online Resource</emphasis>: Enter
        information about online resources for the map, such as where a user
        may download it, etc. This information should include a link, the link
        type (protocol) and a description of the resource.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Reference system info</emphasis>: Enter
        information about the spatial reference system of your map. The
        <emphasis role="bold">default view contains</emphasis> one element to
        provide the <emphasis role="bold">alphanumeric value</emphasis>
        identifying the reference system used. GNos uses the <emphasis
        role="bold">EPSG codes</emphasis> which are numeric codes associated
        with coordinate system definitions. For instance, EPSG:4326 is
        Geographic lat-long WGS84, and EPSG:32611 is "UTM zone 11 North,
        WGS84". Using elements <emphasis role="bold">from the advanced
        view</emphasis>, you may add <emphasis role="bold">more
        details</emphasis> on <emphasis role="bold">data
        projection,</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">ellipsoid</emphasis> and
        <emphasis role="bold">datum</emphasis>. Note that if this information
        is provided, a reference system identifier is not mandatory.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Quality</emphasis>: Specify the
        hierarchal level of the data (<emphasis role="bold">dataset
        series</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">dataset</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">features</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">attributes</emphasis>, etc.) and provide a <emphasis
        role="bold">general explanation on the production processes</emphasis>
        (lineage) used for creating the data. The statement element is
        mandatory if the hierarchical level element is equal to
        <firstterm>dataset</firstterm> or <firstterm>series</firstterm>.
        Detailed information on <emphasis role="bold">completeness, logical
        consistency</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="bold">positional</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">thematic</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">temporal
        accuracy</emphasis> can be directly added <emphasis role="bold">into
        the advanced form</emphasis>.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Metadata Author<emphasis
        role="bold"><emphasis role="bold"> *</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>:
        Provide information about the author of the map, including the
        person’s name, organization, position, role and any other contact
        information available.</para>

        <para>After completion of this section, you may select the <emphasis
        role="bold">Type</emphasis> of document that you are going to save in
        the catalogue. You have three options: <emphasis
        role="bold">Metadata</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">Template</emphasis>, <emphasis
        role="bold">Sub-template</emphasis>. By default <emphasis
        role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> is set up.</para>

        <para>When done, you may click <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis>
        or <emphasis role="bold">Save and Close</emphasis> to close the
        editing session.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>- Creating a Thumbnail</title>

        <para>Next, you need to create a graphic overview of your map which
        will be for a double purpose; as small thumbnail will be displayed in
        search results and as large thumbnail with much more details, to allow
        users to properly evaluate the data usefulness. As for the latest, the
        image that you will use as source should be a significant reproduction
        of the real dataset, possibly inclusive of the legend.</para>

        <para>To create a thumbnail, go to the editing menu for your map. If
        you are no longer in editing mode, retrieve the map from one of the
        search options then click on <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>.
        Then follow these simple steps:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From the editing menu, click on the <emphasis
            role="bold">Thumbnails</emphasis> button on the top or bottom of
            the page. (See figure 7.2.2 a)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.2 a</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/thumButton.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You will be taken to the <emphasis role="bold">Thumbnail
            Management</emphasis> page. (See figure 7.2.2 b)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To create a small or large thumbnail, click on the <emphasis
            role="bold">browse</emphasis> button next to either one. It is
            recommended that you use 180 pixels for small thumbnails and
            800x600 for large thumbnails. Using the ‘Large thumbnail’ option
            allows you to create both a small and large thumbnail in one
            go.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can use GIF, PNG and JPEG images as input for the
            thumbnails.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A pop up window will appear allowing you to browse your
            files on your computer. <emphasis role="bold">Select</emphasis>
            the file you wish to create a thumbnail with by double-clicking on
            it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Your thumbnail will be added and displayed on the following
            page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can then click on <emphasis role="bold">Back to
            Editing</emphasis> and save your record. (See figure 7.2.2
            c)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.2 b</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/thumbManag.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.2 c</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/thumbManag2.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Linking data for download</title>

        <para>Finally, you can upload the dataset stored on your local
        computer and then create a link between data and related description.
        Files in whatever format can be uploaded: doc, PDF, images, vector
        layers, etc. For the latter the distribution in a compressed file is
        recommended. You can include the verctor data, the legend, any
        documentation that can help the interpretation of the data, related
        reports, detailed descriptions of the data processing, base data used
        to create the dataset specified and/or other relevant information.
        Follow these guidelines for uploading datasets:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure the total size of the compressed file is
            reasonable (less than 50 MB). Should your data be bigger than
            50MB, consider a different mechanism to serve this data, e.g.
            through an FTP or HTTP server and than link the resource through
            an online resource ‘Web address (URL)’.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can create several smaller files when appropriate and
            upload them sequentially.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You add the size of the file at the end of the description
            field.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <para>To Upload a Dataset, follow these steps (see figure
        7.2.3):</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">URL</emphasis> field can be left
            empty when uploading a file. The system will automatically fill
            this field out;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the correct <emphasis role="bold">protocol</emphasis>
            to be used. If you do not see the buttons to browse and upload
            when File for download is selected, save the metadata and return
            to the upload section. Both buttons should appear;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Provide a short <emphasis role="bold">description</emphasis>
            of the data;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Browse</emphasis> button and
            navigate to the folder where the file to be released is stored.
            Consider if you want to upload multiple files as one unique zip
            file or as multiple separate downloads. It is a good idea to add
            additional documentation with the datasets that provide the user
            with information related to the data described. Remind: the size
            of a single file to upload can't exceed 50 Mbytes;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Upload</emphasis> and then
            <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.3</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/uploadData.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Assigning Privileges for a Map</title>

        <para>As an important step of entering metadata to your map, you need
        to assign privileges for each map. This means that you will identify
        which work groups have which privileges, i.e. view, download, etc. for
        your particular map.</para>

        <para>For instance, you can fdefine if the information and related
        services is visible to all (Internet users) or just to internal users
        only (Intranet). Privileges are assigned on a per group basis.
        Depending on the user profile (Guest, Registered User, Editor, Admin
        etc.) access to these functions may differ on a per user basis.</para>

        <para>To assign privileges for your map, follow these steps:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Find your map by using the search option. Whether you have
            multiple or single results from the search, on top of the
            individual record or next to the record you will always see a row
            of buttons including a Privileges button. (See figure 7.2.4
            a)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.4 a</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/privilegesButton.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the Privileges button. This will take you to a new
            page. You can assign certain privileges to specific groups by
            selecting or deselecting them from this page. Simply click on the
            small box next to the privilege to place or remove a checkmark.
            <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">Set
            Al</emphasis>l</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Clear
            All</emphasis> buttons allow you to place and remove the
            checkmarks all at once (see figure 7.2.4 b).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.4 b</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/privilegesSetting2.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>

        <para></para>

        <para>Below is a brief description for each privilege to help you
        identify which ones you should assign to which group(s).</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Publish</emphasis>: Users in the specified
        group/s are able to see the map, i.e. if searching with matching
        criteria.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Download</emphasis>: Users in the
        specified group/s are able to download the map.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Interactive Map</emphasis>: Users in the
        specified group/s are able to get an interactive map. <emphasis
        role="bold">The interactive map</emphasis> has to be created
        separately using a Web Map Server, which is part of the GeoNetwork
        opensource application.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Featured</emphasis>: When selected, the
        map is placed in the Features Maps of the home page and it appears
        there randomly.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Notify</emphasis>: Users in that work
        group receive notification that the map has been uploaded.</para>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Assigning Categories for a Map</title>

        <para>As a final step to entering metadata for a map, you should
        assign categories for it. The assigned categories will determine the
        categories the map will display under on the home page. To assign
        categories for a map, follow these steps:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Find your map by using the search option. Whether you have
            multiple or single results from your search, on top of the
            individual record or next to the record, you will always see a row
            of buttons including a <emphasis role="bold">Categories</emphasis>
            button. (See figure 7.2.4 a).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Categories</emphasis>
            button. This will take you to a new page. You can assign one or
            multiple categories selecting or deselecting them from this page.
            Simply click on the small box next to the category to place or
            remove a checkmark. (See figure 7.2.5)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para></para>

        <figure>
          <title>Figure 7.2.5</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../images/categoriesManag.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Uploading a New Record using the XML Metadata Insert Tool</title>

      <para>A more advanced procedure to upload a new metadata record in the
      GeoNetwork system is using an XML document. This procedure is
      particularly useful for users who already have metadata in XML format,
      for instance created by some GIS application. To this regard, it has to
      be noted that the metadata must be in one of the standards used by
      GeoNetwork: ISO19115, FGDC and Dublin Core.</para>

      <para>To start the metadata uploading process through the <emphasis
      role="bold">XML Metadata Insert</emphasis> tool, you should log in (see
      Step. 1. in paragraph 7.1.1) and select the appropriate option from the
      Administration page (Figure 7.3 a).</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 7.3 a</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/xmlUploadButton.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <para>The main part of the page <emphasis role="bold">Import XML
      Formatted Metadata</emphasis> that is displayed (figure 7.3 b) is the
      <emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> text area, where the user can
      paste the XML metadata to import. Below this, there is the <emphasis
      role="bold">Type</emphasis> choise, which allows you select the type of
      record that you are going to create (Metadata, Template and
      Subtemplate). Then you can apply a stylesheet to convert your metadata
      input from ArcCatalog8 to ISO1915 or from ISO19115 to ISO19139, if
      required. Otherwise you can just leave <replaceable>none</replaceable>
      selected. The <emphasis role="bold">Destination schema</emphasis> list
      provides you with four options to choose the final standard layout for
      your metadata (ISO19115, ISO19139, FDGDC and Dublin Core). Finally you
      should select the <emphasis role="bold">Group</emphasis> as main group
      in charge of the metadata and the <emphasis
      role="bold">Category</emphasis> that you want to assign to your
      metadata. By clicking the <emphasis role="bold">Insert</emphasis> button
      the metadata is imported into the system; please note that all links to
      external files, for istance to thumbnails or data for download, have to
      be removed from the metadata input, to avoid any conflict within the
      data repository.</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 7.3 b</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/xmlImporTool.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis></emphasis></emphasis></para>

      <para>If your metadata is already in ISO19115 format, the main actions
      to be performed are the following (Figure 7.3 c):</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Paste the XML file that contains the metadata information in
          the <emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> text area;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select Metadata as <emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> of
          record that you are going to create</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the metadata schema ISO19139 that will be the final
          <emphasis role="bold">destination schema</emphasis>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">validate</emphasis> check box
          if you want your metadata to be validated according to the related
          schema.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">group</emphasis> in charge of
          the metadata from the drop down list;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">Maps and Graphics</emphasis> from
          the list of categories;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Insert</emphasis> button and
          the metadata will be imported into the system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 7.3 c</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/xmlImporTool2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Administration Features</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Creation of new Group Profiles</title>

      <para>The user with administrative privileges can manage the creation of
      various groups corresponding to the various contributors/users of the
      database (e.g. in the FAO-GeoNetwork node you may find as many groups as
      GIS Projects that produce general geographic information in different
      fields of activities: Fishery, Agriculture, Land and Water, Health
      etc).</para>

      <para>To create new groups you should first of all authenticate yourself
      and determine if you have the required administrative privileges. To log
      in, simply go to the homepage and enter your username and password in
      the top right corner fields (use admin for both username and password),
      then click on the login button (figure 8.1a).</para>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 8.1 a</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/login.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the Administration page displayed, select the option
          related to group management (see figure 8.1 b).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 8.1 b</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/AdminManag.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To include a new group in the system, you have to apply the
            following logical steps:</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the Group Management page click on the button <emphasis
          role="bold">Add a new group</emphasis>;</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Figure 8.1 c</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/GroupManag.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Provide the information related to the new group that you are
          going to create;</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Figure 8.1 d</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/addGroup.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Depending on the data owner settings, for each record inserted in
      the system, each group will have different data accessibility privileges
      in relation to: view of Metadata (<emphasis
      role="bold"><emphasis>Publish</emphasis></emphasis>), data Download,
      Interactive Map visualization, view of your map appearing on the home
      page randomly (Featured), Notification when a file gets
      downloaded.</para>

      <para>Below is an example of the privileges management table concerning
      a certain dataset (figure 8.1 e).</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Figure 8.1 e</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/privilegesSetting2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>User Profiles</title>

      <para>Each group has a number of users with different profiles
      (administrator, user administrator, content reviewer, editor, registered
      user) varying in number with respect to the group
      composition/organization (e.g., one administrator, two user
      administrators, two content reviewers, five editors and one registered
      user profile).</para>

      <para>User profiles are illustrated in details in the list below:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Administrator Profile</para>

          <para>The Administrator has special privileges that allow for
          several management activities:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Full rights for creating new groups and new users</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Rights to change users/groups’ profiles</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Full rights for creating/editing/deleting new/old
              metadata</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>User Administrator Profile</para>

          <para>The User Administrator is the administrator of his/her own
          group with the following privileges:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Full rights on creating new users within the own
              group</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rights to change users profiles within the own
              group</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Full rights on creating/editing/ deleting new/old data
              within the own group</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Content Reviewer Profile</para>

          <para>The content reviewer is the only person allowed to give final
          clearance on the metadata publication on the Intranet and/or on the
          Internet:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Rights on reviewing metadata content within the own group
              and authorizing its publication</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Editor Profile</para>

          <para>The User Administrator is the administrator of his/her own
          group with the following privileges:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Full rights on creating/editing/ deleting new/old data
              within the own group</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Registered User Profile</para>

          <para>The User Administrator is the administrator of his/her own
          group with the following privileges:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Right to download protected data</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Creation of new User Profiles</title>

      <para>To include a new user in the GeoNetwork system you will have to
      apply the following logical steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">User Management</emphasis> from
          the Administration link in the toolbar (figure 8.3 a);</para>

          <para></para>

          <figure>
            <title>Figure 8.3 a</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/UserManag.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the button <emphasis role="bold">Add a new
          user</emphasis> to the Database (figure 8.3 b);</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Figure 8.3 b</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/AddUser.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Provide the <emphasis role="bold">information</emphasis>
          required for the new user (figure 8.3 c);</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Figure 8.3 c</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/InsertUserInfo.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Assign the correct <emphasis
          role="bold">profile</emphasis>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Assign the user to a <emphasis
          role="bold">group</emphasis>;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> (figure 8.3
          c).</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <appendix>
    <title>Glossary of Metadata Fields Description</title>

    <para>This glossary provides you with brief descriptions of the minimum
    set of metadata fields required to properly describe a geoghaphical data
    as well as some optional elements highly suggested for a more extensive
    standard description. Note: the <emphasis role="bold">mandatory <emphasis>
    fields are in bold in the following list.</emphasis></emphasis></para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="left" morerows="">Metadata Elements</entry>

            <entry align="left">Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Access
            constraints</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>access constraints applied to assure the protection of
            privacy or intellectual property, and any special restrictions or
            limitations on obtaining the resource</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Abstract </emphasis></entry>

            <entry>brief narrative summary of the content of the
            resource(s)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Administrative area</entry>

            <entry>state, province of the location</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
            role="bold"><emphasis>Temporal extent - </emphasis> Begin
            date</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Formatted as 2007-09-12T15:00:00
            (YYYY-MM-DDTHH:mm:ss)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Character set</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>full name of the character coding standard used for the
            metadata set</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis role="bold">Cell
            geometry</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>identification of grid data as point or cell</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>City</entry>

            <entry>city of the location</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Reference System Info -
            </emphasis>Code</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>alphanumeric value identifying an instance in the
            namespace</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Country</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>country of the physical address</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Data quality info</entry>

            <entry>provides overall assessment of quality of a
            resource(s)</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Date </emphasis></entry>

            <entry>reference date and event used to describe it
            (YYYY-MM-DD)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Date stamp</entry>

            <entry>date that the metadata was created
            (YYYY-MM-DDThh:mm:ss)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Date type</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>event used for reference date</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Delivery
            point</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>address line for the location (as described in ISO 11180,
            annex A)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Equivalent scale</emphasis>
            - Denominator </emphasis></entry>

            <entry>the number below the line in a vulgar fraction</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Data Quality
            </emphasis> - <emphasis
            role="bold">Description</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>description of the event, including related parameters or
            tolerances</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>OnLine
            resource</emphasis> -
            <emphasis>Description</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>detailed text description of what the online resource
            is/does</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Descriptive keywords</entry>

            <entry>provides category keywords, their type, and reference
            source</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis
            role="bold">Dimension name</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>name of the axis i.e. row, column</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis
            role="bold">Dimension size</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>number of elements along the axis</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Dimension size Resolution</entry>

            <entry>number of elements along the axis</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Distribution info</entry>

            <entry>provides information about the distributor of and options
            for obtaining the resource(s)</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Geographic bounding
            box</emphasis> - East bound longitude</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>eastern-most coordinate of the limit of the dataset extent,
            expressed in longitude in decimal degrees (positive east)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry align="left"><emphasis
            role="bold"><emphasis>Edition</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>version of the cited resource</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Electronic mail
            address</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>address of the electronic mailbox of the responsible
            organization or individual</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Temporal extent</emphasis>
            - End date </emphasis></entry>

            <entry>Formatted as 2007-09-12T15:00:00
            (YYYY-MM-DDTHH:mm:ss)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Equivalent scale</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>level of detail expressed as the scale of a comparable
            hardcopy map or chart</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Extent</entry>

            <entry>information about spatial, vertical, and temporal
            extent</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis
            role="bold"><emphasis>Facsimile</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>telephone number of a facsimile machine for the responsible
            organization or individual</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>File identifier</entry>

            <entry>unique identifier for this metadata file</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Vector spatial representation - <emphasis
            role="bold">Geometric object type</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>name of point and vector spatial objects used to locate
            zero-, one-and two-dimensional spatial locations in the
            dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Vector spatial representation - Geometric object
            count</entry>

            <entry>total number of the point or vector object type occurring
            in the dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Geographic bounding box</entry>

            <entry>geographic position of the dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation</entry>

            <entry>information about grid spatial objects in the
            dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis
            role="bold">Resolution value</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>degree of detail in the grid dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation <emphasis role="bold">-
            Transformation parameter availability </emphasis></entry>

            <entry>indication of whether or not parameters for transformation
            exists</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Data Quality <emphasis role="bold"> - Hierarchy
            level</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>hierarchical level of the data specified by the
            scope</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Identification info</entry>

            <entry>basic information about the resource(s) to which the
            metadata applies</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Point of Contact
            </emphasis>- Individual name</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>name of the responsible person- surname, given name, title
            separated by a delimiter</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis
            role="bold"><emphasis>Keyword</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>commonly used word(s) or formalised word(s) or phrase(s)
            used to describe the subject</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Data </emphasis>
            <emphasis>Language</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>language used for documenting data</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Metadata -
            Language</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>language used for documenting metadata</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Data Quality</emphasis> -
            Lineage</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>non-quantitative quality information about the lineage of
            the data specified by the scope. Mandatory if report not
            provided</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>OnLine resource</emphasis>
            - Linkage</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>location (address) for on-line access using a Uniform
            Resource Locator address or similar addressing scheme such as
            http://www.statkart.no/isotc211</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Maintenance and update
            frequency</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>frequency with which changes and additions are made to the
            resource after the initial resource is completed</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Metadata author</entry>

            <entry>party responsible for the metadata information</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Metadata standard
            name</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>name of the metadata standard (including profile name)
            used</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Metadata standard
            version</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>version (profile) of the metadata standard used</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>OnLine resource -
            Name</emphasis></emphasis></entry>

            <entry>name of the online resource</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Geographic bounding box - <emphasis role="bold">North bound
            latitude</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>northern-most, coordinate of the limit of the dataset
            extent expressed in latitude in decimal degrees (positive
            north)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis role="bold">Number
            of dimensions</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>number of independent spatial-temporal axes</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Distribution Info - OnLine resource</entry>

            <entry>information about online sources from which the resource
            can be obtained</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Point of Contact -
            </emphasis>Organisation name</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>name of the responsible organization</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Other constraints</entry>

            <entry>other restrictions and legal prerequisites for accessing
            and using the resource</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Point of contact</entry>

            <entry>identification of, and means of communication with,
            person(s) and organizations(s) associated with the
            resource(s)</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Point of contact -
            </emphasis>Position name</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>role or position of the responsible person</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Postal code</entry>

            <entry>ZIP or other postal code</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Presentation form</entry>

            <entry>mode in which the resource is represented</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>OnLine resource - Protocol</entry>

            <entry>connection protocol to be used</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Purpose</entry>

            <entry>summary of the intentions with which the resource(s) was
            developed</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Reference system info</entry>

            <entry>description of the spatial and temporal reference systems
            used in the datasetData</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Data Quality -<emphasis role="bold">
            Report</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>quantitative quality information for the data specified by
            the scope. Mandatory if lineage not provided</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis
            role="bold">Resolution value</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>degree of detail in the grid dataset</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Point of contact - <emphasis
            role="bold">Role</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>function performed by the responsible party</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Geographic bounding box <emphasis role="bold">- South bound
            latitude</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>southern-most coordinate of the limit of the dataset
            extent, expressed in latitude in decimal degrees (positive
            north)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Spatial representation info</entry>

            <entry>digital representation of spatial information in the
            dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Spatial representation type</entry>

            <entry>method used to spatially represent geographic
            information</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>Data Quality</emphasis> -
            Statement</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>general explanation of the data producer's knowledge about
            the lineage of a dataset</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Status</entry>

            <entry>status of the resource(s)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Supplemental Information</entry>

            <entry>any other descriptive information about the dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Temporal Extent</entry>

            <entry>time period covered by the content of the dataset</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Titel</entry>

            <entry>name by which the cited resource is known</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Topic category
            code</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>high-level geographic data thematic classification to
            assist in the grouping and search of available geographic data
            sets. Can be used to group keywords as well. Listed examples are
            not exhaustive. NOTE It is understood there are overlaps between
            general categories and the user is encouraged to select the one
            most appropriate.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Grid spatial representation - <emphasis
            role="bold">Transformation parameter
            availability</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>indication of whether or not parameters for transformation
            exists</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Vector spatial representation - Topology level</entry>

            <entry>code which identifies the degree of complexity of the
            spatial relationships</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Type</entry>

            <entry>subject matter used to group similar keywords</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>URL</entry>

            <entry>URL</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Use constraints</entry>

            <entry>constraints applied to assure the protection of privacy or
            intellectual property, and any special restrictions or limitations
            or warnings on using the resource</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Vector spatial representation</entry>

            <entry>information about the vector spatial objects in the
            dataset</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Voice</entry>

            <entry>telephone number by which individuals can speak to the
            responsible organization or individual</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Geographic bounding box -<emphasis role="bold"> West bound
            longitude</emphasis></entry>

            <entry>western-most coordinate of the limit of the dataset extent,
            expressed in longitude in decimal degrees (positive east)</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </appendix>

  <appendix>
    <title>ISO Topic Categories</title>

    <para>Isotopic Categories and Keywords</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/ISOCategory.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/ISOCategory2.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/ISOCategory3.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </appendix>

  <appendix>
    <title>Free and Open Source Software for Geospatial Information
    Systems</title>

    <para>A range of geospatial related software packages can be implemented
    in addition to GeoNetwork opensource to deploy a full Spatial Data
    Infrastructure. Within the range of Free and Open Source Software (FOSS)
    solutions, these may include Web Map Server software, GIS desktop
    applications and Web Map Viewers.</para>

    <para>Below you will find some examples of open source software available
    for each categories. Note that the FOSS in following list are downloadable
    from the Sourceforge web site http://www.sourceforge.net.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Web Map Server software</emphasis>:</para>

    <para>MapServer (All)*</para>

    <para>MapGuide (Windows &amp; Linux)</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">GIS Desktop software</emphasis>:</para>

    <para>GRASS (All)*</para>

    <para>gvSIG (Windows &amp; Linux)</para>

    <para>uDIG (All)*</para>

    <para>OSSIM (Windows &amp; OSX)</para>

    <para>Quantum GIS (All)*</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Web Map Viewers</emphasis>:</para>

    <para>OpenLayers (All)*</para>

    <para>MapBender (All)*</para>

    <para>MapBuilder (All)*</para>

    <para>Ka-Map 1.0b1 (All)*</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>* All = Windows, Linux and Mac OS X</para>
  </appendix>
</book>