<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter
        id="metadata_ownership">
        <title>Metadata ownership</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Starting from release 2.1.0, GeoNetwork has a new metadata access policy. The old
                edit and admin privileges have been removed and the concept of reviewer has been
                introduced. The purpose of this new profile is to control when a metadata can be
                published outside or not. In previous releases, all users belonging to a group with
                edit privileges could edit the same metadata. Now, a metadata is only visible to its
                creator, to a reviewer which has access to the group owner and to an
                administrator.</para>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Access policy</title>

            <para>A public metadata is a metadata that has the view privilege for the group named
                all.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Visualisation</title>
                <para>An administrator can view any metadata.</para>

                <para>A reviewer can view a metadata if:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The metadata owner is member of one of the groups assigned to the
                            reviewer.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>She/he is the metadata owner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>A user administrator or an editor can view:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All metadata that has the view privilege selected for one of the
                            groups she/he is member of.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All metadata created by her/him.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>A registered user can view:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All metadata that has the view privilege selected for one of the
                            groups she/he is member of.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>Public metadata can be viewed by any user (logged in or not).</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Editing</title>
                <para>An administrator can edit any metadata.</para>

                <para>A reviewer can edit a metadata if:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The metadata owner is member of one of the groups assigned to the
                            reviewer.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>She/he is the metadata owner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>A User Administrator or an Editor can only edit metadata she/he
                    created.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Privileges</title>

            <para>The Privileges administration page is accessible only by:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>All Administrators</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>All Reviewers that are member of one of the groups assigned to the
                        metadata owner.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Owner of the metadata</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Privileges for the All and Intranet groups can only be edited by Administrators
                and Reviewers.</para>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Transfer Ownership</title>
            <para>When metadata ownership needs to be transferred from one user to another for all
                or specific metadata records, the Transfer Ownership option is available. It is
                located in the Administration page (<xref
                    linkend="admin_ownership_where" />) and once selected, leads to the page shown
                in <xref
                    linkend="admin_ownership_options" />.</para>

            <figure
                id="admin_ownership_where">
                <title> How to open the Transfer Ownership page </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="images/admin/web-ownership-where.png"
                            width="11cm"
                            align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Initially, the page shows only a dropdown for a Source editor (the current
                metadata owner). The dropdown is filled with all GeoNetwork Users that have the
                Editor role and own some metadata. Selecting an Editor will select all metadata that
                is managed by that Editor. An empty dropdown means that there are no Editors with
                metadata associated and hence no transfer is possible.</para>
            <para>Note The drop down will be filled with all Editors visible to you. If you are not
                an Administrator, you will view only a subset of all Editors.</para>

            <figure
                id="admin_ownership_options">
                <title> The Transfer Ownership page </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="images/admin/web-ownership-options.png"
                            width="9cm"
                            align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Once a Source Editor has been selected, a set of rows is displayed. Each row
                refers to the group of the Editor for which there are privileges. The meaning of
                each column is the following:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Source group</emphasis>: This is a group that has privileges in
                        the metadata that belong to the source editor. Put in another way, if one of
                        the editor’s metadata has privileges for one group, that group is listed
                        here.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Target group</emphasis>: This is the destination group of the
                        transferring process. All privileges relative to the source group are
                        transferred to the target group. The target group drop down is filled with
                        all groups visible to the logged user (typically an administrator or a user
                        administrator). By default, the Source group is selected in the target drop
                        down. Privileges to groups All and Intranet are not transferable.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Target editor</emphasis>: Once a Target group is selected, this
                        drop down is filled with all editors that belong to that Target
                        group.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Operation</emphasis>: Currently only the Transfer operation is
                        possible.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>By selecting the Transfer operation, if the Source group is different than the
                Target group, the system performs the Transfer of Ownership, shows a brief summary
                and removes the current row because now there are no privileges to transfer
                anymore.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
