<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <glossary
        id="glossary">
<!--        <glossentry
            id="glos-ebrim">
            <glossterm>ebRIM</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Enterprise Business Registry Information Model..</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry> -->
        <glossentry
            id="glos-csw">
            <glossterm>CSW</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Catalog Service for the Web. The OGC Catalog Service defines common interfaces 
                    to discover, browse, and query metadata about data, services, and other potential resources.</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="glos-ogc"/>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-iso">
            <glossterm>ISO</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>International Standards Organisation is an international-standard-setting body 
                    composed of representatives from various national standards organizations. <ulink url="http://www.iso.org"></ulink>.</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="glos-tc211"/>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry id="glos-tc211">
            <glossterm>ISO TC211</glossterm>
            <glossdef><para>ISO/TC 211 is a standard technical committee formed within ISO, 
                tasked with covering the areas of digital geographic information (such as 
                used by geographic information systems) and geomatics. It is responsible 
                for preparation of a series of International Standards and Technical 
                Specifications numbered in the range starting at 19101.</para></glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <glossentry
            id="glos-gn">
            <glossterm>GeoNetwork</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>GeoNetwork opensource is a standards based, Free and Open Source catalog 
                    application to manage spatially referenced resources through the web.<ulink url="http://geonetwork-opensource.org"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-gn1">
            <glossterm>GN</glossterm>
            <glosssee
                otherterm="glos-gn" />
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry id="glos_cc">
        	<glossterm>CC</glossterm>
        	<glossdef>
        		<para>GeoNetwork documentation is released under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.
        Find more information at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/</para>
        	</glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-xml">
            <glossterm>XML</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Extensible Markup Language is a general-purpose specification for 
                    creating custom markup languages.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-xsd">
            <glossterm>XSD</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>XML Schema, published as a W3C recommendation in May 2001, is one of 
                    several XML schema languages. <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XSD" /></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
<!--        <glossentry
            id="glos-ebxml">
            <glossterm>ebXML</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Enterprise Business XML.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-dao">
            <glossterm>DAO</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Data Access Object.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-crud">
            <glossterm>CRUD</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Create Read Update and Delete.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry> -->
        <glossentry
            id="glos-db">
            <glossterm>DB (or DBMS)</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A database management system (DBMS) is computer software that 
                    manages databases. DBMSes may use any of a variety of database models, 
                    such as the network model or relational model. In large systems, 
                    a DBMS allows users and other software to store and retrieve data 
                    in a structured way.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-soa">
            <glossterm>SOA</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Service Oriented Architecture provides methods for systems 
                    development and integration where systems package functionality 
                    as interoperable services. A SOA infrastructure allows different 
                    applications to exchange data with one another.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry id="glos-fgdc">
            <glossterm>FGDC</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Federal Geographic Data Committee (FGDC) is an interagency committee 
                    that promotes the coordinated development, use, sharing, and dissemination of 
                    geospatial data on a national basis in the USA. See <ulink url="http://www.fgdc.gov"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <!--        <glossentry
            id="glos-jms">
            <glossterm>JMS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Java Messaging Service.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-tdd">
            <glossterm>TDD</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Test Driven Development.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-jibx">
            <glossterm>JIBX</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Binding XML to Java Code.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-hql">
            <glossterm>HQL</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Hibernate Query Language.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-oo">
            <glossterm>OO</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Object Oriented.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-ejb">
            <glossterm>EJB</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Enterprise Java Beans.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry> -->
        <glossentry
            id="glos-soap">
            <glossterm>SOAP</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Simple Object Access Protocol is a protocol specification for 
                    exchanging structured information in the implementation of Web 
                    Services in computer networks.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-ogc">
            <glossterm>OGC</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Open Geospatial Consortium. A standards organization for geospatial 
                    information systems <ulink url="http://www.opengeospatial.org"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-osgeo">
            <glossterm >OSGeo</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Open Source Geospatial Foundation (OSGeo), is a non-profit 
                    non-governmental organization whose mission is to support and 
                    promote the collaborative development of open geospatial technologies 
                    and data. <ulink url="http://www.osgeo.org"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-fao">
            <glossterm>FAO</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Food and Agriculture Organisation of the United Nations is a specialised 
                    agency of the United Nations that leads international efforts to defeat 
                    hunger. <ulink url="http://www.fao.org"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-wfp">
            <glossterm>WFP</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>World Food Programme of the United Nations is the food aid branch 
                    of the United Nations, and the world's largest humanitarian 
                    organization. <ulink url="http://www.wfp.org"></ulink></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-unep">
            <glossterm>UNEP</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The UN Environment Programme (UNEP) coordinates United Nations 
                    environmental activities, assisting developing countries in implementing 
                    environmentally sound policies and encourages sustainable development 
                    through sound environmental practices. <ulink url="http://www.unep.org"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-ocha">
            <glossterm>OCHA</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs 
                    is designed to strengthen the UN's response to complex emergencies 
                    and natural disasters. <ulink url="http://ochaonline.un.org/"></ulink></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-url">
            <glossterm>URL</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A Uniform Resource Locator specifies where an identified resource 
                    is available and the mechanism for retrieving it.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-gast">
            <glossterm>GAST</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>GeoNetwork Administrator Survival Tool. A desktop application 
                    that allows administrators of a GeoNetwork catalog to perform a 
                    range of admin operations.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-webdav">
            <glossterm>WebDAV</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Web-based Distributed Authoring and Versioning. WebDAV is a set of extensions to the 
                    Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) that allows users to edit and manage files 
                    collaboratively on remote World Wide Web servers.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-oaipmh">
            <glossterm>OAI-PMH</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Open Archive Initiative Protocol for Metadata Harvesting. 
                    It is a protocol developed by the Open Archives Initiative. 
                    It is used to harvest (or collect) the metadata descriptions 
                    of the records in an archive so that services can be built using 
                    metadata from many archives.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-wms">
            <glossterm>WMS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Web Map Service is a standard protocol for serving georeferenced 
                    map images over the Internet that are generated by a map server using 
                    data from a GIS database. The specification was developed and first 
                    published by the Open Geospatial Consortium in 1999.</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="glos-ogc"/>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-wfs">
            <glossterm>WFS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Web Feature Service provides an interface allowing requests for 
                    geographical features across the web using platform-independent calls. 
                    One can think of geographical features as the "source code" behind a map.</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="glos-ogc"/>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-wcs">
            <glossterm>WCS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Web Coverage Service provides an interface allowing requests for 
                    geographical coverages across the web using platform-independent calls. 
                    The coverages are objects (or images) in a geographical area</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="glos-ogc"/>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-wps">
            <glossterm>WPS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Web Processing Service is designed to standardize the way that 
                    GIS calculations are made available to the Internet. WPS can describe 
                    any calculation (i.e. process) including all of its inputs and outputs, 
                    and trigger its execution as a Web Service.</para>
                <glossseealso otherterm="glos-ogc"/>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-uuid">
            <glossterm>UUID</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>A Universally Unique Identifier 
                    (UUID) is an identifier standard used in software construction, 
                    standardized by the Open Software Foundation (OSF) as part of the 
                    Distributed Computing Environment (DCE).</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-mac">
            <glossterm>MAC address</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Media Access Control address (MAC address) 
                    is a unique identifier assigned to most network adapters or network 
                    interface cards (NICs) by the manufacturer for identification, 
                    and used in the Media Access Control protocol sublayer. 
                    See also <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAC_address">MAC address</ulink>
                    on Wikipedia</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-mef">
            <glossterm>MEF</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Metadata Exchange Format. An export format developed by the GeoNetwork community. 
                    More details can be found in this manual in Chapter Metadata Exchange Format.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-skos">
            <glossterm>SKOS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Simple Knowledge Organisation Systems (SKOS)
                    <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/"/> is an area of work developing
                    specifications and standards to support the use of knowledge organisation systems
                    (KOS) such as thesauri, classification schemes.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-z3950">
            <glossterm>Z39.50 protocol</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Z39.50 is a client-server protocol for searching and retrieving information 
                    from remote computer databases. It is covered by ANSI/NISO standard Z39.50, 
                    and ISO standard 23950. The standard's maintenance agency is the Library of Congress.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-smtp">
            <glossterm>SMTP</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol is an Internet standard for electronic
                    mail (e-mail) transmission across Internet Protocol (IP) networks.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-ldap">
            <glossterm>LDAP</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol is an application protocol 
                    for querying and modifying directory services running over TCP/IP.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-shibboleth">
            <glossterm>Shibboleth</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Shibboleth System is a standards based, open source software package 
                    for web single sign-on across or within organisational boundaries. It allows 
                    sites to make informed authorisation decisions for individual access of 
                    protected online resources in a privacy-preserving manner.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-dc">
            <glossterm>DC</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Dublin Core metadata element set is a standard for cross-domain 
                    information resource description. It provides a simple and standardised 
                    set of conventions for describing things online in ways that make them easier to find.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-esa">
            <glossterm>ESA</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>European Space Agency is an intergovernmental organisation dedicated 
                    to the exploration of space. <ulink url="http://www.esa.int"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-foss">
            <glossterm>FOSS</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>Free and Open Source Software, also F/OSS, FOSS, or FLOSS 
                    (free/libre/open source software) is software which is liberally 
                    licensed to grant the right of users to study, change, and improve 
                    its design through the availability of its source 
                    code. <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FOSS"/></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry
            id="glos-jdbc">
            <glossterm>JDBC</glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para>The Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) API is the industry standard for 
                    database-independent connectivity between the Java programming language and a 
                    wide range of databases – SQL databases and other tabular data sources, such 
                    as spreadsheets or flat files. The JDBC API provides a call-level API for 
                    SQL-based database access.</para>
                 <para>JDBC technology allows you to use the Java programming language to exploit 
                    "Write Once, Run Anywhere" capabilities for applications that require access 
                    to enterprise data. With a JDBC technology-enabled driver, you can connect 
                    all corporate data even in a heterogeneous environment.</para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <!--        <glossentry
            id="glos-">
            <glossterm></glossterm>
            <glossdef>
                <para></para>
            </glossdef>
        </glossentry> -->
        
    </glossary>
</book>
