<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
   <para>Catalogue Service for the Web. The OGC Catalogue Service defines common interfaces to discover, browse, and query metadata about data, services, and other potential resources.</para>
   <para>International Standards Organisation is an international-standard-setting body composed of representatives from various national standards organizations. .</para>
   <para>ISO/TC 211 is a standard technical committee formed within ISO, tasked with covering the areas of digital geographic information (such as used by geographic information systems) and geomatics. It is responsible for preparation of a series of International Standards and Technical Specifications numbered in the range starting at 19101.</para>
   <para>GeoNetwork opensource is a standards based, Free and Open Source catalogue application to manage spatially referenced resources through the web.</para>
   <para>Extensible Mark-up Language is a general-purpose specification for creating custom mark-up languages.</para>
   <para>XML Schema, published as a W3C recommendation in May 2001, is one of several XML schema languages. </para>
   <para>A database management system (DBMS) is computer software that manages databases. DBMS may use any of a variety of database models, such as the network model or relational model. In large systems, a DBMS allows users and other software to store and retrieve data in a structured way.</para>
   <para>Service Oriented Architecture provides methods for systems development and integration where systems package functionality as interoperable services. A SOA infrastructure allows different applications to exchange data with one another.</para>
   <para>The Federal Geographic Data Committee (FGDC) is an inter agency committee that promotes the coordinated development, use, sharing, and dissemination of geospatial data on a national basis in the USA. See </para>
   <para>Simple Object Access Protocol is a protocol specification for exchanging structured information in the implementation of Web Services in computer networks.</para>
   <para>Open Geospatial Consortium. A standards organization for geospatial information systems </para>
   <para>The Open Source Geospatial Foundation (OSGeo), is a non-profit non-governmental organization whose mission is to support and promote the collaborative development of open geospatial technologies and data. </para>
   <para>Food and Agriculture Organisation of the United Nations is a specialised agency of the United Nations that leads international efforts to defeat hunger. </para>
   <para>World Food Programme of the United Nations is the food aid branch of the United Nations, and the world's largest humanitarian organization. </para>
   <para>The UN Environment Programme (UNEP) coordinates United Nations environmental activities, assisting developing countries in implementing environmentally sound policies and encourages sustainable development through sound environmental practices. </para>
   <para>United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs is designed to strengthen the UN's response to complex emergencies and natural disasters. </para>
   <para>A Uniform Resource Locator specifies where an identified resource is available and the mechanism for retrieving it.</para>
   <para>GeoNetwork Administrator Survival Tool. A desktop application that allows administrators of a GeoNetwork catalogue to perform a range of admin operations.</para>
   <para>Web-based Distributed Authoring and Versioning. WebDAV is a set of extensions to the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) that allows users to edit and manage files collaboratively on remote World Wide Web servers.</para>
   <para>Open Archive Initiative Protocol for Metadata Harvesting. It is a protocol developed by the Open Archives Initiative. It is used to harvest (or collect) the metadata descriptions of the records in an archive so that services can be built using metadata from many archives.</para>
   <para>Web Map Service is a standard protocol for serving georeferenced map images over the Internet that are generated by a map server using data from a GIS database. The specification was developed and first published by the Open Geospatial Consortium in 1999.</para>
   <para>Web Feature Service provides an interface allowing requests for geographical features across the web using platform-independent calls. One can think of geographical features as the "source code" behind a map.</para>
   <para>Web Coverage Service provides an interface allowing requests for geographical coverages across the web using platform-independent calls. The coverages are objects (or images) in a geographical area</para>
   <para>Web Processing Service is designed to standardize the way that GIS calculations are made available to the Internet. WPS can describe any calculation (i.e. process) including all of its inputs and outputs, and trigger its execution as a Web Service.</para>
   <para>A Universally Unique Identifier (UUID) is an identifier standard used in software construction, standardized by the Open Software Foundation (OSF) as part of the Distributed Computing Environment (DCE).</para>
   <para>Media Access Control address (MAC address) is a unique identifier assigned to most network adapters or network interface cards (NICs) by the manufacturer for identification, and used in the Media Access Control protocol sub-layer. See also <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAC_address">MAC address</ulink> on Wikipedia</para>
   <para>Metadata Exchange Format. An export format developed by the GeoNetwork community. More details can be found in this manual in Chapter Metadata Exchange Format.</para>
   <para>The Simple Knowledge Organisation Systems (SKOS) is an area of work developing specifications and standards to support the use of knowledge organisation systems (KOS) such as thesauri, classification schemes.</para>
   <para>Z39.50 is a client-server protocol for searching and retrieving information from remote computer databases. It is covered by ANSI/NISO standard Z39.50, and ISO standard 23950. The standard's maintenance agency is the Library of Congress.</para>
   <para>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol is an Internet standard for electronic mail (e-mail) transmission across Internet Protocol (IP) networks.</para>
   <para>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol is an application protocol for querying and modifying directory services running over TCP/IP.</para>
   <para>The Dublin Core metadata element set is a standard for cross-domain information resource description. It provides a simple and standardised set of conventions for describing things online in ways that make them easier to find.</para>
   <para>European Space Agency is an intergovernmental organisation dedicated to the exploration of space. </para>
   <para>Free and Open Source Software, also F/OSS, FOSS, or FLOSS (free/libre/open source software) is software which is liberally licensed to grant the right of users to study, change, and improve its design through the availability of its source code. </para>
   <para>The Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) API is the industry standard for database-independent connectivity between the Java programming language and a wide range of databases – SQL databases and other tabular data sources, such as spreadsheets or flat files. The JDBC API provides a call-level API for SQL-based database access.</para>
   <para>JDBC technology allows you to use the Java programming language to exploit "Write Once, Run Anywhere" capabilities for applications that require access to enterprise data. With a JDBC technology-enabled driver, you can connect all corporate data even in a heterogeneous environment.</para>
</article>