<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article lang="">
   <para>Viewing and Analysing the Data</para>
   <para>Once you have completed your search, you view details of a particular record by clicking on the <emphasis>Metadata</emphasis> button.</para>
   <para>The metadata profiles used by GNos to present and describe geographic data and general documents stored in the catalogue are based on the<emphasis> International Standard</emphasis> 
      <emphasis>ISO 19115:2003</emphasis>, encoded according to the <emphasis>implementation schema</emphasis> 
      <emphasis>19139:2007</emphasis>, the <emphasis>FGDC</emphasis> and the international standard <emphasis>Dublin Core</emphasis>.</para>
   <para>In this guide the <emphasis>ISO 19139</emphasis> metadata implementation will be described in details since it is also suggested as profile for the creation of new metadata records.</para><sect1><title>Meta Data Description</title>
   <para>Meta Data Description</para>
   <para>The metadata ISO 19139 profile used by GeoNetwork opensource to describe the geographic data and services is based on the ISO standard 19115:2003 and provides information related to the identification, the maintenance and constraints, the spatial and temporal extent, the spatial representation and reference, the quality and distribution of a geographic dataset.</para>
   <para>The metadata profile is organized in sections and the most important, illustrated in , are the: <emphasis>Identification Section, Distribution Section, Reference System Section, Data Quality Section and Metadata Section</emphasis>. These sections are described here in details.</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/mainSections.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject><sect2><title>Identification Section</title>
   <para>Identification Section</para>
   <para>This section includes information on the citation of the resource (<emphasis>title, date of creation or publication, edition, presentation form</emphasis>), the <emphasis>abstract</emphasis>, the <emphasis>purpose</emphasis> and the present<emphasis> status</emphasis> of the resource that can be defined among the options: completed, historical archive, obsolete, ongoing, planned, required or under development. ().</para>
   <para> </para>
   <para>This section also contains information about the person or organization responsible for the data and who is considered to be a <emphasis>point of contact</emphasis> for the resource i.e. the dataset owner, originator, distributor, publisher, etc. and it provides information on <emphasis>data maintenance</emphasis> i.e. annually, monthly, daily, not planned, as needed, etc. ()</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/PoC_Maint.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject>
   <para>Elements for <emphasis>keywords</emphasis> and for describing restrictions on <emphasis>data</emphasis> 
      <emphasis>access</emphasis> and <emphasis>use</emphasis> are also included in this section in addition to <emphasis>spatial representation </emphasis>info like data type (vector, raster, text table, etc.) ().</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/Key_Const_Spatype.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject>
   <para>The identification section provides information about the <emphasis>scale</emphasis>, the <emphasis>language</emphasis> and <emphasis>character set</emphasis> used within the resource and the list of <emphasis>ISO categories</emphasis> through which your map could be classified ().</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/scale.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject>
   <para>Finally, the temporal and spatial extent are also defined in this section. The temporal extent is defined through the starting and ending date of data validation ();</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/temp_extent.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject>
   <para>The spatial extent of the interested area is defined through geographic coordinates or through the selection of a country or region from a predefined list (). Free text <emphasis>supplemental information</emphasis> can be added to complete the data identification section.</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/geobox.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject></sect2><sect2><title>Distribution Section</title>
   <para>Distribution Section</para>
   <para>This section provides metadata elements for <emphasis>accessing</emphasis> other useful <emphasis>on-line resources</emphasis> available <emphasis>through the web</emphasis>. The distribution elements allow for on-line access using an URL address or similar addressing scheme and provide the protocol for the proper connection <emphasis>for accessing geographic data</emphasis> or any other types of digital documents <emphasis>using the download</emphasis> 
      <emphasis>function</emphasis>. Furthermore, it is possible <emphasis>to link</emphasis> a metadata with a <emphasis>predefined map service</emphasis> through the <emphasis>on line resource</emphasis> and see the map interactively ().</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/distrInfo.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject></sect2><sect2><title>Reference System Section</title>
   <para>Reference System Section</para>
   <para>The Spatial Reference System section <emphasis>defines</emphasis> 
      <emphasis>metadata</emphasis> required <emphasis>to describe</emphasis> the <emphasis>spatial reference system</emphasis> of a dataset. It contains one element to identify the name of the reference system used (). Using elements <emphasis>from the advanced form</emphasis>, this section may be modified to provide more <emphasis>details</emphasis> on <emphasis>data projection</emphasis>, <emphasis>ellipsoid</emphasis> and <emphasis>datum</emphasis>. Note that if this information is provided, a reference system identifier is not mandatory.</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/RefSystem.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject></sect2><sect2><title>Data Quality Section</title>
   <para>Data Quality Section</para>
   <para>The Data Quality section provides a <emphasis>general assessment</emphasis> of the <emphasis>quality of the data</emphasis>. It describes the<emphasis> different hierarchical levels of data quality</emphasis>, namely a <emphasis>dataset series</emphasis>, <emphasis>dataset</emphasis>, <emphasis>features</emphasis>, <emphasis>attributes</emphasis>, etc. This section also contains information about <emphasis>sources of the input data</emphasis>, and a<emphasis> general explanation of the production processes</emphasis> (lineage) used for creating the data ().</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/dataQuality.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject></sect2><sect2><title>Metadata Information Section</title>
   <para>Metadata Information Section</para>
   <para>This section contains information about the metadata itself: the <emphasis>Global Unique Identifier</emphasis> (GUID) assigned to the record (this is the ‘File identifier’), <emphasis>language</emphasis> and <emphasis>character</emphasis> 
      <emphasis>set</emphasis> used, <emphasis>date</emphasis> of <emphasis>last edit</emphasis> (‘Date stamp’) and the <emphasis>metadata standard</emphasis> and <emphasis>version name</emphasis> of the record. It also contains information on the <emphasis>metadata author</emphasis> responsible for the metadata record; this person can also be a point of contact for the resource described. Information on the Metadata author is mandatory ().</para>
   <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="#images/metadata.png"/>
         <caption/>
      </imageobject> 
   </mediaobject></sect2></sect1></article>